Okay,
it's 10.30,
so we'll get started,
good to see everyone.
I made a post on Ed yesterday
with all of the details about
midterm one, so make sure you
read that.
But the big ideas are,
it's in a week from today,
Tuesday, October 6th, from 7 to
9 p.m.
in 10.13
DAO, which is just across the
hall.
Everything we have covered so
far is in scope, including this
week's lectures.
But Thursday's lecture will
mostly be review of the stuff we
talk about today.
So we're not going to learn
anything brand new on Thursday
that will be on the exam.
Otherwise, all homeworks,
labs,
and chapters one to four of the
course notes are in scope.
The types of questions you can
expect to see, you'll see a mix
of multiple choice,
short answer,
and more long form homework
style questions.
And if you go to
exams.ex245.org,
You can see all of our past
exams, so all past midterm ones,
twos, and finals.
But as I said in that post,
we are going to do a practice
exam this upcoming Friday
from 2.30
to 5.30,
also in 10.13
DAO, so the same room the real
midterm is going to be in.
And the way that's going to work
is from 2.30
to 4.30,
we are going to have printed out
copies of the spring 26 midterm
one.
And you can come in and take
that as if it's a real exam.
So we will put a timer on the
board You can't talk XYZ So I
want to like simulate that exam
environment where you're like
solving problems under time
pressure and then from 4 30 to 5
30 We'll take it up and answer
any questions you may have and
that part is recorded
Okay, so all that is to say if
you're looking at past exams
this week And you're going to
come to the mock exam on Friday.
Don't look at the spring 26
midterm.
Okay?
In addition,
in terms of notes, you can bring
one double-sided handwritten
regular sheet of paper.
By handwritten, we mean you have
to actually write it yourself on
paper unless you have
accommodations that allow
otherwise.
You can't write it on an iPad
and then print it because that's
how you get everything really
small.
Not supposed to do that.
You've got to write it yourself
on a regular piece of paper.
Okay any questions about the
exam itself or review for
it?
All good?
Okay other announcements this is
slightly wrong but it'll be true
later today.
Homework four was released on
Friday and we are going to make
it due on Sunday instead of
Friday just to give you a little
bit of extra time to work on But
no slip days are allowed.
Okay.
This is effectively.
We're just giving everyone We're
like using up to slip days on it
But you don't have to use your
own slip days and this is so
that we can release the
solutions on Monday morning So
you can study till Tuesday and
part of this later deadline is
because some of the questions
involve stuff from today's
lecture
Okay,
homework three solutions are up
and I'm gonna update the grade
report tomorrow with your
scores on homework three plus
tomorrow's lab
It says the scores are up, but
they're not quite yet.
We're still like doing a bit of
manual review, but you can
expect to see all of that
tomorrow.
And yeah, the other big thing is
the practice.
Any logistical questions?
All good?
Okay.
The plan for today is to start
by discussing something that we
meant to actually discuss in
last week's lab.
And there are several questions
about it in this week's
homework, which is finding the
equation of a plane.
We'll look at one example of
this.
Then we will review the big idea
from last Thursday, Which is the
span of D vectors in Rn.
What is that? And what are some
of the possible configurations
of say the span of three vectors
in R3 or five vectors in R2?
That's like the kind of thing we
started discussing on Thursday.
Then we will formalize that idea
Which involves introducing this
term called linear independence
Which will be a term that comes
up a lot today and moving
forward and then Formalizing
those ideas will be the idea of
a vector space and a subspace
Which sounds like it's a new
thing, but remember I've already
been using the term subspace So
I want to just introduce some
formal language around that and
then Thursday's lecture will be
just continuing all of this
okay, so
What I want to start with
And I want to give you a chance
to work on this before I take it
up is an activity from chapter
4.4
It's asking us to find the
equation in standard form of two
different planes.
And let me make this a little
bigger.
Okay.
Can someone remind me what the
equation of a plane in standard
form is? form looks like.
Like, what is the template of
that, Sofia?
A x plus b y plus c z plus d
equals 0.
equals 0,
OK?
And so what this is giving us is
two examples
of pairs of vectors in R3,
and it's asking for the equation
of the plane that they span in
this form, a x plus b y plus c z
plus d equals 0.
So what I want you to do is take
a few minutes,
think about how you might
approach this.
Maybe you did already do this in
last week's lab, but if I
remember correctly, the TAs told
me that you didn't get a chance
to in many sections.
So attempt this and see where
you get, and then we will take
it up.
and feel free to discuss with
those near you.
That's the equation.
Yeah.
So we're covering pretty well.
The equations.
You better react.
You know what I'm saying? I'm
going to go ahead and open it.
I'm going to take a look at
this.
So make some assumptions.
Go.
What happened?
It's basically being able to
find.
Open the thing again.
Go on the way.
We have dark white, dark green,
simultaneously,
yeah.
Find.
1030 code zero, 4HN, that's the
word, my
threshold is 11 o'clock, if it's
11 it feels like late enough in
the day.
and zero,
zero in this equation.
How about the, I would do it
like that.
Because if z becomes like zero,
you know that like,
the derivative
with respect to the first
component,
I'm the x-directional.
I feel like,
hey,
you can like, remember that z is
the x,
y, and z is the x, y, and z is
the x, y, and z is the x,
y, and z.
But we have to get these on the
sides before you open it.
Give us another minute to
discuss here.
Matthew, did you get the plate?
Thank you.
I'm just not logged in.
Yeah.
When they said that we had to
have our cheat sheets submitted
by Wednesday at noon, I was
like,
oh my god.
Really?
Yeah.
I was like, not this month.
Not tomorrow, but like next
month.
Did you think just the next
month are taking the exam and
I'm like why can't we just turn
it off and like bring it back to
the classroom because we don't
want it to be like this.
That's the plane, that is the
plane.
Yeah,
but I think it needs a little
help.
It's fine.
It actually does a lot of work.
It's just a plane.
It's like I have someone like
you and I'm like crazy and then
you're gonna be trapped in the X
bar.
It's not really happening.
Oh, that's great.
It's too dirty.
It's not sleeping.
OK, let's start with the first
pair of vectors.
We ask you for the equation of
the plane in standard form
for the plane spanned by the
vectors 3, 2, 0 and negative 1,
1, 0.
And what we mean by equation of
the plane is this plane equation
describes all of the vectors of
the form x, y, z
that live on the plane.
So the a,
b, c, and d values I find should
be such that if I plug in 3 for
x,
2 for y, 0 for z,
the equation is true.
And if I plug in negative 1 for
x,
1 for y,
0 for z,
the equation should also be
true.
So in this first case, how did
you find A, B, C, and D?
What's that one? It's a cross
product.
OK, and what did that tell you?
That tells you the orthogonal
vector to both vectors.
Good.
So that's one thing I want to
emphasize here.
First,
we know what this value of D is
going to be in both of these
cases.
What is D going to be in both of
these cases?
You didn't need to do any
calculation.
And I could have told you what
the plus d was going to be.
What is that here?
Yeah.
0.
Why?
Isn't it because the plane of
any two vectors
crossed the origin?
Exactly.
The span of any number of
vectors,
remember that's the set of all
of their linear combinations.
The 0 vector needs to be one of
those linear combinations,
because I could create that by
taking 0 of the first vector
plus 0 of the second vector.
What that means is whatever
equation I find,
it should be true when I plug in
x equals
0,
y equals 0, and z equals 0.
But notice if I plug in x equals
0, y equals 0, and z equals 0,
then the first three terms, ax
plus by plus cz,
all get zeroed out.
What that tells you is d also
has to be equal to 0.
OK?
So this is 0 when the plane
passes
through the 0 vector.
Now, not every plane needs to
pass through the 0 vector, but
then the planes that don't
contain the 0 vector
aren't the span of two vectors.
OK,
so here we know that this plus d
term is going to be 0.
So we can just focus on finding
Ax plus By plus Cz equals 0.
In that,
our goal is to find the A,
B, and C.
And as you mentioned,
what we're looking for, if you
stare at this equation,
is you're looking for another
vector of the form ABC,
such that when you take any
vector on the plane,
x, y, z,
and dot product it with ABC, you
find that they're orthogonal.
Do you agree with that?
So you can think of a plane as
being defined by a vector who is
perpendicular to everything on
the plane.
So the picture you should have
in your mind is that if this is
the plane we're dealing with,
then this is the vector ABC.
Now the vector ABC is not unique
because 2a, 2b, 2c would also
still point in the same
direction.
And if I took that first
equation and multiplied both
sides by 2, it would still be
true for all vectors x, y, z
that are on the plane.
So all we need is one of the
infinitely many vectors that are
perpendicular to this plane.
And so as chapter 4.4
in the notes tells you,
the cross product is an
operation
that takes in two vectors in R3
and gives you back one of the
infinitely many vectors that's
perpendicular to both of them.
So that's what the cross product
does.
You pick any two vectors in R3.
Pretend their span is this iPad
tilted or the case of the iPad.
What the cross product will tell
you is one of the many vectors
that either point this way or
this way.
The thing is the length of the
vector that you get back from
the cross product, in some
engineering applications, has
some meaning.
But we don't really care about
that right now.
We just want one of the many
vectors in that direction.
Right, but like the cross
product could point this way It
could point this way and it
depends on what order you put
the vectors into the cross
product Okay,
but for our purposes we just
want one of the vectors that's
perpendicular to that point And
so in this case, yeah We could
use the cross product and it
would tell us a vector and tell
me what what vector did the
cross product give You I'm gonna
give me zero zero five.
It gave you zero zero something
Okay,
and so if the cross product
gives you back zero zero five,
what's that what that telling
you?
or what that's telling you.
And in the next example, we will
actually work it out.
But suppose you found that the
cross product is 0, 0, 5.
What that's telling you is that
the equation of this plane is 0x
plus 0y plus 5z equals what?
0.
0, good.
But if I simplify this a little,
the 0x and 0y can go away.
And I'm really just left with 5z
equals 0.
But then I'm really just left
with z equals 0.
So that is a perfectly valid
equation of a plane.
And if we consult our friend
Desmos over here,
and we type in z equals 0,
that's a perfectly fine plate.
It's a set of all vectors in R3
whose z component is 0.
Now, knowing that that's what
the answer ends up being,
can you think of a way we could
have done this without the cross
product?
Yeah,
Alex?
Because both z components of the
vector is 0, we know that the
span is trapped on the xy plane.
Exactly.
Now, if we look at the two
vectors that we were given, 3,
2, 0, negative 1, 1, 0,
we know that both of them are
trapped on the xy plane.
They both had zeros in that
third component.
So knowing that we know that all
you need are two vectors in R3
to define a plane,
what that tells you is that all
linear combinations of these two
vectors at the top,
3, 2, 0, and negative 1, 1, 0,
are forced to have a z value of
0.
So the plane that they span is
just all vectors with a z value
of 0.
What about the second one,
three, two, four,
negative one,
one,
two?
How might we proceed here?
First I'll note that the cross
product is not the only way to
proceed.
Remember what we are looking
for,
if you go back to that picture,
if this is the plane spanned by
these two vectors,
we're looking for a vector,
which we might call the normal
vector.
Normal meaning perpendicular
here.
That is orthogonal to both 3, 2,
4 and negative 1, 1, 2.
You don't need to know anything
about a cross product to find
that.
It's just that the cross product
is like a surefire formula that
tells you one possible normal
vector.
But how might you do this
otherwise?
You could set up a system of
equations.
You can say, pretend that normal
vector is ABC.
I'll write that term here,
normal.
Pretend that vector is ABC.
Well, then the dot product of
ABC with three, two, four
should be zero.
Now, let me just annotate here.
This is just three,
two, four dotted with ABC.
And then the dot product of ABC
with negative one,
one,
two should also be zero.
And what you could do is just
find one combination of A, B,
and C that satisfy this.
Of course, there will be
infinitely many,
and that corresponds to the fact
that there are infinitely many
vectors that are perpendicular
to this plane.
So, we should expect that there
are infinitely many solutions
for A, B, and C.
OK, so you can play around with
these equations,
and you can find a combination
of A, B, and C that satisfy
this.
That's a perfectly valid way to
do it.
The cross product just tells you
one of them.
It tells you a specific one that
has some geometric
interpretation beyond the fact
that it's perpendicular to both
3, 2, 4, and negative 1, 1, 2.
But we're not going to care much
about the length of the cross
product here.
We're just going to use it as
being a tool that tells us one
of the many vectors
perpendicular to both of these.
OK.
Can someone?
I'm going to erase this picture
up here,
because it's the same picture
from before, though I should go
back in here, say, this is a
normal vector,
just so the pictures are there.
Can someone tell me how you
would find the cross product
of 3, 2, 4?
It's written with the regular
multiplication symbol,
negative 1, 1, 2.
What does that end up being?
Sorry.
It's all right.
You want the final answer?
Tell me how you got it.
I write like i, j,
k,
and then I do like 3, 2, 4,
negative 1, 1, 2, and then put a
pencil over the i and do the
determinant of the other four
components.
So that is one way you can do
it, but that requires knowing
something about a determinant,
which we'll only cover in like a
month or something.
But the general idea that you
just said holds true as well
here
you start with the second
component and you do a 2 times
b 3 or let's say u 2 times v 3
Minus these two things
multiplied so it would be 2
times 2 minus 1 times 4.
What does that give you?
Then you do the next pair 4
times negative 1
minus 3 times 2 What does that
give you?
Negative 10.
And then lastly,
3 times 1 minus 2 times negative
1.
What does that give you?
3 minus negative 2, that's
positive 5.
So what that tells you is the
plane equation
is 0x minus 10y plus 5z equals
0.
That's where these numbers are
coming from.
But you can simplify this a
little to what?
What's the nicer way to write
this?
Yeah.
0, negative 2, 1.
Good.
I could notice that all I'm
really looking for is one vector
that's perpendicular to both.
And it looks nicest if the
numbers in the equation are as
small as they need to be.
So what I could do is just
divide both sides of this
equation by negative 5.
And what that would tell you is
that the equation of the plane
is also 2y minus z equals 0.
And that can't really be further
simplified.
So this is the set of all
vectors whose z component
is double their y component in
R3.
That's all this is really
saying.
Right? This says y equals 2z.
We should double check that the
vectors we started with satisfy
this.
Does 3, 2, 4 satisfy that?
Yeah, sure.
4 is double 2.
And does negative 1, 1, 2
satisfy that? Sure, 2 is double
1.
So that means both vectors
satisfy this equation.
That means we found the right
plane equation.
OK?
The two examples we've worked
through
ended up giving us rather simple
looking equations, like z equals
0 and 2y minus z equals 0.
But in general,
if this was a 1 that we got back
in the cross product,
then the equation would have
been x minus 10y plus 5z equals
0, and that's a perfectly valid
equation.
The bigger picture here is that
the cross product tells us a way
of finding one of these normal
vectors,
but don't rely on that as the
only way.
Sometimes there is information
in the question or the situation
that tells you more naturally a
vector that is perpendicular to
the spanning vectors.
Like here,
you don't need to use the cross
product.
You can just look at this and
tell that 0, 0, 1 would be
orthogonal to both of these
vectors.
Or if you look at old exam
questions,
there's one that says,
here are three vectors that are
all perpendicular to each other
in R3.
Find the equation of the plane
spanned by the first two.
And I remember on that question,
a lot of people took the cross
product.
But the cross product just told
you that it was equal.
like the cross product was just
the third vector.
Because we told you all three of
the vectors were perpendicular
to each other.
So if I tell you that, then you
don't need to take the cross
product of these two.
You can just use the third one
that I gave you.
That's the kind of thinking I
want you to use here.
By the way, the cross product,
the reason I'm not covering it
in depth in class is because
it's a very specific thing that
only works for two vectors in
R3.
Because what it tells you is the
direction that is perpendicular
to both of them.
But that's only a thing that
works in R3.
Imagine we're thinking in R4,
where there's like four
independent directions in which
you can move.
There's no one direction that is
perpendicular to the span of two
vectors.
There's lots of directions that
are perpendicular to the span of
two vectors.
And so the cross product, it's
like a very specific thing.
It's only for two vectors in R3.
The dot product, on the other
hand, works for two vectors in
any universe.
And it's more general,
which is why we spend much more
time talking about it.
Let me emphasize that here.
Questions with that so far?
Yeah,
Gavin and then Paul.
Oh, me first? Yeah, sure.
OK.
So we were saying that the
equation for a plane
is when the dot product equals
0.
Why is that the case?
Well,
if we go back to here,
first, we reasoned about why the
d here has to be 0.
Then we're just left with ax
plus by plus cz equals 0.
But if you just look at this, it
looks like the dot product of x,
y, z with a, b, c.
Interesting.
OK.
Yeah.
So this is saying all vectors x,
y, z,
like if x, y, and z are the
components of the vector,
if that vector satisfies this
equation, well then it's
orthogonal to a, b, c.
That would force it to be on
that plane because if not, it
wouldn't be orthogonal.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Good.
Paul.
I think I have two questions.
Sure.
So is the only time we would
ever really need to use the
cross product if the question
was explicitly,
like, find the plane equation?
Find the plane equation, yes.
Also,
is there intuition for why it's
like A2, B3 minus A3, B2,
like the specific values you're
multiplying in each vector?
Yeah, good question.
If you really want to see where
the cross product comes from,
what you could do,
it would take some time, it's
messy.
take this setup and just replace
this with u1,
u2,
u3,
v1,
v2,
and v3 and try and solve for
what A, B, and C would have to
be.
And you see that the
multiplication of u2, v3 is like
that enters the picture when you
try and solve there for a
general solution.
Yeah.
Good question.
So finding that orthogonal to
the plane,
to the span of the two of these
two vectors,
what does that make? That
doesn't make the vector on the
plane.
Correct, correct.
So like here,
the vector 0, negative 10, 5 is
definitely not on the plane.
It's perpendicular to everything
on the plane.
And that fact is how we found
the equation for the plane.
So here,
like,
let's start with the two vectors
I told you about.
Pretend,
I mean, this is just, you know,
a picture,
but pretend that's the vector 3
2 4.
This is the vector negative 1 1
2.
By the way, these vectors don't
have to be orthogonal.
I mean, they could be, but
that's That's unrelated to the
question.
Imagine this is the plane
spanned
by,
let's just call these vectors u
and v.
The cross product told us this,
0, negative 10, 5
is perfectly perpendicular to
everything on the plane.
But 0,
negative 10, 5 is definitely not
on the plane.
In fact, it's like as far as you
could be from the plane.
But the reason it's useful is
because it tells us that every
vector on the plane
satisfies
0, negative 10, 5 dot
producted with that vector,
which why don't we call it x, y,
z equals 0.
But that right there tells you
the equation for the plane.
It just says every vector that
satisfies the plane equation
should have negative 10 y plus
5z equals 0.
Does that kind of help?
Good,
these are all great
clarifications.
When you did the cross,
you had some kind of cross thing
that you did.
Can you show how you did that
for the other numbers?
You took the diagonal of the
bottom two.
This, this? Yeah, the next would
be,
I mean,
one way that it's often
visualized, and you should look
at the notes for this, But you
could write a 3,
and you repeat the first two
elements, and then you can keep
going.
So I would put 3, 2 here, and
negative 1, 1 here, and I'd have
the first cross,
the second cross, and then the
third cross.
All right.
Yeah.
But again, I'm intentionally not
spending that much time on this
in class, because I don't want
you to think it's as important
as the dot product.
This is sort of like a tool that
we use to answer one type of
question.
The dot product, on the other
hand,
we use all the time for lots of
things.
OK,
great questions.
What other questions do we have
about this?
Why should we use the ijk method
for the cost product? Oh,
because we haven't talked about
what i, j, and k are.
And we haven't talked about what
a determinant is.
OK.
So that was a tangent.
Remember,
one of the last things we talked
about on Thursday was thinking
about what the various numbers
of vectors could span in R2,
and then R3, and then R
anything,
R17 was the running example I
used.
So the first thing we looked at
was one vector.
As long as that vector is not
the zero vector,
then whether we're working in
R2,
or R3,
or R17, or R54,
what is the span of one vector?
Just a single vector.
What does it span? A line.
A line,
good.
And this is one of the first
times we encountered having to
think beyond our ability to
visualize.
We said the span of one vector
in R17
is a line in R17.
Then we talked about two
vectors,
and we said two vectors in R2,
as long as they don't point in
the same direction,
what was their span?
Two vectors in R2,
As long as they didn't point in
the same direction.
Yeah,
a plane and in R2 there is only
one plane.
It's just everything right your
XY plane
What about two vectors in R3
what are the possible things
they could spend
Two vectors in R3.
It's not what it says on the
board, but two vectors in R3 We
saw that there were three
possible things that they could
spend
Good that's only the case when
they don't point in the same
direction Right?
And that's the example we just
worked through,
or the two examples we just
worked through.
In both cases,
this being the first one and
this being the second one, I
gave you two vectors in R3 that
didn't point in the same
direction.
And what I got back was the
plane that they span.
OK?
But they only span a plane when
the two vectors don't point in
the same direction to begin
with.
If they did point in the same
direction,
well then, if you think about it
from the cross-product
perspective,
there are infinitely many
vectors that are perpendicular
to both of these.
Like this one is perpendicular,
but so is this one, and so is
this one.
There's a whole circle of
vectors that are perpendicular
to that one direction.
The final case we started to
look at was three vectors in R3.
What were the four possible
things that they could span?
What was the most edge case of
this? The zero vector.
The zero vector.
That's if they're all the zero
vector.
OK, what was the next case?
A line.
That would happen if all three
of your vectors
pointed in the same direction.
What's the next case?
Yeah,
a plane.
When would you get three vectors
is an R3 spanning a plane?
Well, it's if two vectors span a
plane, and then the third one is
also just on that same plane.
It doesn't allow you to escape
the plane.
That is not the situation with
the three vectors drawn here.
But imagine I have u and v,
and my third vector was like
some linear combination of u and
v, like it also lived on this
plane.
Well, then if I have that linear
combination of u and v,
it doesn't allow me to escape
the plane.
So I'm still trapped to that
slice of R3 that the first two
vectors span.
And then what's the last
possibility?
All of R3.
Okay, and there was a term I
used to refer to a line.
It was a blank dimensional...
subspace...
of r blank.
What did I call this line?
Yeah,
it's a one-dimensional subspace
of r what?
Yeah, not quite.
Remember that vectors we're
working with here are in R3.
So nothing about this situation
will be related to R2.
And that's a common
misconception.
Students often think that a
plane in R3 is the same as R2.
But R2, for example,
is just the set of all vectors
with two numbers in them.
And this plane,
while it's two dimensional and
that when you're on it you can
only move in two
independent directions,
every vector on it has three
things in it, which means it
lives in R3.
So what should go here?
3 good
Then what about this plane?
What is that?
kind of already said it but
How would I describe this with
that terminology?
Yeah, I'd call this a
two-dimensional
Subspace of r3 good
So we've seen several examples
of this.
Now I want to come up with a
general definition or a general
understanding of what some
number of vectors in R something
span.
So let's suppose in general we
have
vectors v1,
v2, all the way through vd and
they all live in Rn,
they span a blank
dimensional subspace
of R blank.
How might I fill this in?
So one of these is
straightforward to figure out.
The other one,
there's no one short answer to
this.
What's the easiest thing we
could fill out about this
sentence?
Like,
in general,
the n,
the dimensional subspace of n,
or n.
It's not always n, though.
Right, like what if I have five
vectors in R2,
then n would be 2.
But they all live on the same
line.
Then their span isn't all of R2.
So this answer is not just going
to be a single number.
It's going to depend on the
vectors themselves.
And that's reflective of the
fact that here,
in this example,
we're dealing with vectors in
R3, so n would be 3.
But the dimension of the
subspace spanned by the vectors
is either 0, 1, 2, or 3,
OK?
So let's start with this.
What should I put in, like, it's
R what?
Whatever they span, it's a
subspace of R.
Caitlin?
It's an error,
isn't it?
Good.
Can you please repeat that?
Rn.
Good.
And remember, n is the number of
components in the vector,
in each vector.
Now, what is the dimension of
the subspace band?
Well, what's the smallest
possible answer?
Zero, it could be zero.
All right, what if all the
vectors are the zero vector?
So like whatever thing we put in
the blank here
should account for that
possibility.
So I'm gonna start with a
between zero
and...
Now, what is the max dimension
of the subspace?
Yeah.
N.
It depends on the number of
vectors we have, though.
Because what if I have three
vectors in R7?
It's not possible for them to
span all of R7.
So what is the upper bound then,
Bella?
But what if I have five vectors
in R2?
Then d is 5,
n is 2,
and their span can't be
five-dimensional because they
live in R2.
So what both of your answers
tell us is that there are two
factors that govern what the
upper bound on this is.
If I have five vectors in R2,
there d is 5, n is 2,
the span can be at most
two-dimensional.
If I have three vectors in R7,
their span can be at most
three-dimensional.
So your span can't be,
the dimension of the span can't
be greater than the universe you
live in or the number of vectors
you have.
So the upper bound here is the
smaller of n
and d.
Your span can't be greater in
dimension than the number of
vectors you have or the universe
you live in.
So remember, n is the number of
components in each vector,
and D is the number of vectors,
okay.
Anytime you're faced with a
definition like this, and I
think I said this before, but
it's especially true in terms of
D and N,
what I want you to do is just
make up examples in your mind
and write down on your page,
What is D here? What is N here?
And reason about it.
So suppose we have two vectors
in R4.
Well, here,
D is 2 and N is equal to 4.
So their span,
depending on what they are,
is a 0,
1, or 2 dimensional subspace
of R what?
4.
The vectors are in R4.
So like nothing about them is in
R3, 2, or 1,
OK?
What about four vectors in R2?
Now here,
d is 4,
n is 2,
their span is a 0,
1, or 2
Dimensional subspace of R-what?
Two.
Again, the vectors all live in
R2,
so their span also is something
in R2.
OK.
Questions so far?
Seem OK?
All right.
We're going to do a combined
activity plus attendance, and
I'll give us quite a bit of time
for this.
Here's the activity I want you
to work on.
Find six vectors in R4
that span
a three-dimensional subspace
of
R4.
So what I'm asking you to do is
on your page, write down six
vectors such that together their
span is a three-dimensional
subspace of R4.
I'll say also do attendance.
And it's 11 11.
We'll come back at 11 16 and let
me open the floor
So we're about to define it.
But these computers,
they're perfectly independent.
It's mentioned in my front page,
and it's related to this.
I made them.
I'm using linear combination.
They have a bunch of stuff.
Any two numbers in R2.
That's like an 8K image,
so awesome.
Oh,
yeah.
We had to define that.
We're gonna do that.
You don't need to know that
directly to do this, but you'll,
sort of,
have this.
I feel like all of these people
are being so good.
I mean, they tell me which
things have been pulled up in
lecture yet.
Oh,
yes.
Okay.
I'm gonna do it 10 times one,
so.
This summarizes the whole block.
Like, I'm gonna have something.
I'm gonna have something.
I'm not even sure what it's like
to call it a zero.
Zero two.
Zero zero.
Zero five.
Zero zero zero zero zero zero
zero zero zero zero zero zero
zero zero zero zero
Do you have like Instagram or
whatever it is?
All the things I wanted
to add I just got the answers.
Yeah, um, I guess those are like
the text used for
cross-products.
Really?
I made it.
I know I talked before this.
And then we were like,
What's going on?
And then we were like, Oh my
goodness.
A really massive cartwheel.
And then we were like,
I was going to do a solo,
but I didn't think it would
work.
It's like a small process.
It's like a span.
I think it's like half of what
it's slipping together.
And then it's like,
it's like,
I'm more scared for a 2D one.
Because it's multi-line.
I don't think the OA area looks
good.
Another 30 seconds or
so.
Okay.
Everyone checked in.
Yeah?
Okay.
Let's take a Look,
what I was looking for are six
vectors in R4 that together span
a three-dimensional subspace of
R4.
How did you go about doing this?
Firstly, note that there's no
one answer.
We could have all come up with
different answers.
They could all be right.
How did you go about doing this?
How did you attempt?
Yeah, Alex.
I found we have three
independent vectors and then
just had three scalar multiples
of three vectors.
Good.
And so you use the term they're
independent that we haven't
actually defined it.
That's going to be the next
thing we discuss.
But that's one of the things
this activity is meant to have
you into it, that there's useful
vectors and then vectors you
made using them.
And the main idea here is that
since the span of these six
vectors is a three-dimensional
subspace,
we're supposed to think of three
vectors that each contribute
something new.
And then the other three,
because we had asked for six
total,
should just be things you can
make with those first three.
That's a similar idea to a few
slides ago.
What would it mean for three
vectors in R3 to span just a
plane?
Well we know a plane only needs
two vectors.
So if all three vectors span a
plane, well that means there's
one of them that you don't
really need there.
You could still make the plane
without one of them.
That's what it means for three
vectors to span a
two-dimensional subspace.
One of them is redundant or not
needed.
So similarly here,
I asked for six vectors
that span a three-dimensional
subspace.
What that means is three of the
vectors actually contribute
something meaningful, and three
of them are not necessarily
needed.
OK,
so what's the easiest way to do
this without needing to think
much about the numbers?
How did you approach this, if
you got an answer?
Sure.
I just defined the first vector
as 3 2 1 and I just took a dot
product would be to set it to
zero
Sounds like a lot of work
It would work like it's
perfectly fine But an important
thing though to mention is that
these vector the first three
vectors you write down don't
need to be orthogonal
They can be but orthogonality is
stricter than we asked for
Okay, and I'll define this idea
of independence more clearly in
just a minute But the easier
answer is to just write these
things down.
Does that kind of make sense?
OK.
Now that I got these three down,
these three together, they span
a three-dimensional subspace of
R4.
So all I have to do now is write
down three other vectors
that don't increase the space of
linear combinations I could
make.
What are some of those? Well, I
can take arbitrary linear
combinations of these first
three.
Or I can just be lazy and say 2,
0, 0, 0,
3, 0, 0, 0,
and 4, 0, 0, 0.
Perfectly fine.
OK?
That's not the only possible
answer.
Of course, there's lots of
answers you could give.
I want to just demonstrate
another sort of template.
I didn't need to use just 1, 1
and 3 0's here.
I could have done 1, 0, 0, 0,
0,
1, 1, 0,
0, 0, 1.
And now as long as these other
three vectors I write are linear
combinations of the first three,
this dimension of their span is
still three.
So I don't know.
What's a vector that's a linear
combination of these? 1, 1, 1,
1.
Sure, toss it in there.
What about 17,
44,
12?
Perfectly fine.
Now,
a vector that wouldn't be in the
span of the first three
is if I made this.
OK,
how about this? Let me just
write this down.
1, 2, 3, 4.
Why is that not in the span of
the first three vectors?
Why was it OK to write this
here, but this is wrong.
They kind of look the same.
They're just four random
numbers.
What's the difference?
Yeah?
The second vector is 0,
1, 1, 0.
So if you have 2, 3 in the third
vector, that would be
impossible.
Yeah.
It's impossible to make this
sixth vector, 1, 2, 3, 4,
just using the first three.
Because any linear combination
of the first three It's gonna be
of the form a b b
C what that requires is that the
middle two components of any
linear combination are the same
Which is why I had a 1 1 here
and a 44 44.
I can't make two three So the
span of all of these vectors is
actually all of our four
I'm sorry.
So that means this was not a
good choice.
And instead I got to pick
something else like
1 2 2 4 But it doesn't have to
be a linear combination of all
of them.
I could have just put 7,
0,
0, 0.
Two possible answers.
Why was that example you gave on
the right not
a combination of 0, 0, 0, 1?
Because 0 times 0, 0 times.
It would have used 1, 0, 0, 0,
and 0, 0, 0, 1.
But any linear combination of
the first three vectors here,
like,
if you test it out, just
multiply this by 7,
this by negative 2, this by pi,
multiply all three of them by
whatever you want and add them
up,
the result is going to have a
second and third component that
are the same.
So if I write down a vector
whose second and third
components aren't the same,
then it couldn't be written as a
linear combination of these
three.
Does that kind of make sense?
And it's because this vector
just has one 1 here, And this
vector,
if I put a negative 1 here or
something, or just 17 here, or
something like that, which would
have been a fine example.
It's just not the example I
wrote down.
Then maybe it would have been
possible to make 1, 2, 3, 4.
But with the vectors I wrote
down, it was not possible to
make 1, 2, 3, 4.
OK?
So I guess what I'm saying is
it's not like 1, 2, 3, 4 could
never be in an answer to this
question.
It's just that it couldn't be in
the answer to this question,
given that these are the first
three vectors I wrote down.
But you can make an answer that
has 1, 2, 3, 4 in it.
Good question.
Also, it's worth saying that
these are the first, like, let's
look at the first example.
These are the first three
vectors I wrote down.
And yeah, they span a three
dimensional subspace of R4.
But so do these three vectors.
There's nothing special about
the first one being 1, 0, 0, 0.
I could have written these three
down first and then put 1, 0, 0,
0 later or not had it at all.
And the span of all of these
would still be the same
three-dimensional subspace of
R4.
So what I mean by that is the
order in which I wrote these
vectors down does not matter,
which is why I've written these
as sets of vectors, because in a
set, the order does not matter.
So without expanding it out,
what's the significance of the
middle two values being one that
makes it so that?
That's just an example.
Or what's the,
what attribute of that makes it
so that the other two have to be
the same in the middle?
It's because any vector that is
a linear combination of these
first three is something times
the first plus something times
the second plus something times
the third.
Notice this vector has nothing
in the middle two components and
this vector also has nothing,
which means any non-zero value
in the middle two components is
coming just from this thing.
But in this vector, the middle
two components are equal.
What that means is in any linear
combination of these,
the middle two components would
have to be equal.
So if it was like two and one,
would it have to be like 88 and
44?
Exactly, yeah.
Yeah.
This is just an example I wrote
down because it allows us to
talk about it, but there's
nothing special about 1-1 being
here.
It's just an example I wrote
down.
Good.
These are great questions.
Okay,
so what I want to do now is
formalize the idea that it seems
like we have six vectors here
but they're not all needed to
span this three-dimensional
subspace and it's because
if you look at this set,
some of these vectors can be
made with other vectors that are
in the set.
Okay, some of them are
redundant.
Okay,
and the formalization of this
comes with the term linear
independence.
And this is defined in chapter
4.2.
Okay.
So what I'll do is I'll say
vectors v1,
v2,
vd,
and rn are
said to be linearly independent
if, And here's the first
definition I will write.
None of the vectors
can be written
as linear.
That's the intuitive definition
I want you to have.
So vectors v1 through vd, that
collection, is linearly
independent if none of the
vectors in the collection can be
made with any of the others.
That's the key property here.
So is this set linearly
independent,
the first one?
Is that a linearly independent
collection of vectors?
No,
because I can make 2, 0, 0 using
some of the other vectors that
are there.
I can make 3, 0, 0 using some of
the other vectors that are
there.
I can make 1, 0, 0, 0 using some
of the other vectors that are
there.
So this collection is not
linearly independent.
What about the second
collection? Is it linearly
independent?
No, because I can make this
vector using some of the other
vectors that are here.
I can make this vector 0, 0, 0,
1 by taking 1, 1, 1, 1 and
subtracting this and then
subtracting this.
And I'd be left with 0, 0, 0, 1.
So this collection is not
linearly independent.
There's another equivalent
definition that is slightly more
formal mathematically that we
will use in proofs often,
because this one,
none of the vectors can be
written as linear combinations
of the others.
That's the important definition
I want you to have in your mind,
but it's hard to write that down
algebraically.
There's an equivalent
definition.
It's that vectors are linearly
independent if the only solution
to
a1 times v1,
see if you can predict where
this is going,
plus a2 times v2,
all the way through ad times vd,
equals the zero vector is where
all of the coefficients
are zero.
So there's two equivalent
definitions of a collection of
vectors being linearly
independent.
The first definition is this
collection of vectors is
linearly independent if every
single one of them bring
something new to the table.
You can't make any of them using
the others.
It turns out, and I'm going to
give you some intuition for this
in just a second,
that is the same as saying the
only way you can make the zero
vector using them
is by taking zero of each one.
There's no other way to make the
zero vector.
These are the same definition.
And
I'll say otherwise,
they are linearly
dependent.
OK.
So why are these definitions
related?
Let's come up with an example.
Well,
let's suppose
we
have three vectors, v1, v2, and
v3.
Suppose they all just live in
Rn.
Doesn't matter what universe
they live in.
And that v3 is a linear
combination of the first two.
2v1 plus 7v2.
Are these vectors linearly
independent?
Is this collection of vectors
linearly independent?
No, you're shaking your head no.
Why?
Because v3 is, what's it called?
It's made by v1 and v2.
Good.
Note that for them to be
linearly independent, the
requirement is that none of them
can be written as linear
combinations of the others.
The opposite of none is at least
one.
It doesn't mean that every one
of them needs to be made as
linear combinations of the
others, but because at least
one,
LC just means linear combination
of others.
Why is that? Well, it's because
we told you v3 is equal to 2v1
plus 7v2.
But it turns out with this
equation, you can actually make
all three vectors using the
others.
You can just rearrange it.
So for example,
can I make v1 using the other
two?
Sure, you can.
The numbers are just a little
ugly.
But you solve, you get 2v1
equals negative 7v2 plus v3.
What that means is v1, if you
divide both sides by 2 here,
is negative 7 over 2v2 plus 1
half times v3.
So v3,
there's nothing special about
it.
It's just the one I told you the
most direct equation about.
Either way, these are all
telling us the same thing.
This collection of vectors is
not linearly independent.
By the way, hopefully it's
clear.
The property of linear
independence is a property of a
collection of vectors.
If I just write down the vector
1, 0 and ask, is it linearly
independent, well,
that's not a question that is
defined unless I have a
collection of vectors.
Now, maybe my collection is just
the vector 1, 0.
And is that collection linearly
independent?
Sure, because there's no other
vector to make 1, 0 with.
But a vector on its own,
whether it's linearly
independent or not, that's not a
question you can ask.
The property is of a collection
of vectors.
But my point here was to give
you some intuition for this
second definition of linear
independence.
We know why this collection, v1,
v2, v3, is not linearly
independent.
Because I can make at least one
of them using the others.
What was that second definition
about, and how is that related
to this?
Allison?
The second definition is that we
could only make the zero vector
if we just made all the
coefficients zero.
Good.
Remember, the second definition
of linear independence is we say
this collection of vectors is
linearly independent if the only
way you can make the zero vector
using them is by taking zero of
each one.
Is that the case here?
No,
why not? Yeah.
Can you think of another way to
make the zero vector using the
three vectors v1, v2, and v3?
Yeah.
We need 2v1 plus 7v2 minus v3.
Good.
All this is saying is if at
least one of the vectors can be
made with the others,
then you can rearrange that
equation to make the zero vector
using some of the vectors in a
non-trivial way.
A trivial way would be zero
times each one.
But here what we've seen is that
I was able to make the zero
vector by taking at least one
non-zero scalar.
So do we see this correspondence
between one of the vectors being
redundant and being able to make
the zero vector in a non-trivial
way?
Do you see how those are kind of
related?
OK, good.
By the way, as you'll see in
tomorrow's lab, this second
definition is called the formal
definition.
And you'll do some proofs that
involve the formal definition.
But I want you to have the
intuitive definition in mind.
Vectors are linearly independent
if there's no way to make any
one of them using the others.
Okay, and the like way that I
think about this conceptually
Is that the vectors are linearly
independent if every vector
brings something new to the
table if you're considering
their span
Every vector there is necessary.
If you remove any one of them
the span decreases it removes
some of the vectors that you can
build
Okay
What questions do we have so far
about linear independence
There's one thing in the notes I
want to point out, because
you're going to do this
in lab tomorrow and in
homework this
week.
Two things I want to point out.
OK, actually.
So first,
one of the reasons we care about
vectors being linearly
independent is that there's a
beautiful property of vectors
that are linearly independent,
which is that if you have
vectors that are linearly
independent,
then any of their linear
combinations
can only be made in one way.
I think we briefly talked about
this before.
What that means is if I give you
a collection of building blocks
that are these vectors
v's, and I say they're linearly
independent, what that means is
any other vector I can make
using the building blocks,
there's only one recipe to make
it.
There's only one combination of
scalars that would allow you to
make that output.
It's like, for example,
this is important enough to
write down.
I'll give you an example here.
Suppose I have the vector u
being 1, 0 and the vector v
being 1, 1.
So let's consider the vector
3,
4.
Firstly, do we agree that u and
v are linearly independent?
All that's needed for them to be
linearly independent,
since we're dealing with two
vectors in R2,
is that they don't point in the
same direction.
If they did point in the same
direction, then they'd be scalar
multiples of each other, and you
can make one with the other.
Okay,
notice it's not required that
they're orthogonal.
Orthogonality is like a very
strict condition.
Okay, it's like a even more
supercharged version of linear
independence.
If vectors are orthogonal, then
they're definitely linearly
independent.
But you don't need to be
orthogonal to be linearly
independent.
For example, this U and V are
linearly independent, but
they're not orthogonal.
Okay, so orthogonality is like a
stricter condition.
So these vectors U and V,
they're linearly independent,
which means you can't make
either one with the other.
What that means is anything you
can make with u and v,
there's only one way to make it,
OK?
So let's consider this vector 3,
4.
How do you make it with u and v?
Well, here's how I think about
it.
Only v controls the bottom
component here.
What that means is the number
you multiply v by has to be 4.
Do you agree with that?
There's no other way you're
going to get a 4 down here.
But that would make a 4 up here.
We want a 3.
So what should I multiply u by?
Yeah,
negative 1.
All I'm getting at is that there
is no other numbers you could
multiply u and v by in a linear
combination that would give you
3, 4.
It can't be done.
There's only one way to do it.
But what if I instead have?
U,
v, and let's toss in a
troublemaker here,
0, 1.
It's still true that 3, 4 is
equal to negative 1u plus 4
times v.
But can you think of another
linear combination? And here,
why don't I put a plus 0 w?
But can you think of another
linear combination of these
three vectors that also gives me
3, 4?
Yeah?
3u plus 4w.
Yeah, I could do 3us,
ignore v entirely,
goodbye,
And then take four w's.
Can you think of a way to do
this
in which none of the
coefficients are 0?
Sure, why not?
Just to illustrate how absurd we
can make this,
why do we make it 2026v?
What would you have to adjust
the numbers you multiply u and w
by?
What would the coefficient on u
need to be?
Sorry.
Negative 2023.
Negative 2023, good.
And then what would the number
on w need to be?
Not quite, because here we're at
2026, 2026.
We got rid of 2023 on the top,
but we still need to make the
bottom a 4.
So what should the bottom number
be?
Good.
Negative 2022.
And hopefully it's clear that, I
mean, I picked 2023 or 2026
because it's the current year.
But you could have picked any
number you want.
And you would have been able to
find a linear combination of u,
v, and w that gives you the
vector 3, 4.
And that's because these vectors
are not linearly independent.
When you have vectors that are
not linearly independent,
Their linear combinations are
not unique, okay? What that
means is since I was able to
make 3, 4 and my building blocks
are not linearly independent, I
can make 3, 4 infinitely many
ways.
Here these vectors u and v are
linearly independent, so their
linear combinations are unique.
I'll say this is the only linear
combination
of u and v that equals 3, 4.
Are we clear on that idea?
And if you want a bit more
intuition for where this is
coming from,
it comes from the fact that you
can make, say,
v using u and w,
because u plus w equals v.
What that means is u minus v
plus w equals the 0 vector.
What that means is if you just
start with this linear
combination, you can add
whatever you want times the 0
vector to both sides.
And you're just adding 0 to both
sides, which is allowed.
And you can multiply that
equation, u minus v plus w
equals 0,
by whatever you want.
Multiply it by pi, your
birthday, whatever.
And add it to this equation,
you'll a new linear combination
of u, v, and w that gives you
the zero vector.
How's that?
So, I guess I'm just trying to
make sure I get it.
So if you have all these
linearly independent vectors and
they're all, I mean they're
basically they're all pointing
then in their own directions and
they can't combine into each
other.
Sure.
Yeah, that's one way to think
about it.
That's like the case here.
So then any two of them will
almost like make their own like
two dimensional slice so that
any of their combinations can
only exist with those two
vectors,
since by nature of being
linearly independent, the other
ones just won't exist there.
I think it's the opposite.
It's that if we consider this u
and v here, 1, 0, and 1, 1,
they span all of R2.
So it doesn't matter what third
vector I write.
I happen to write one that looks
convenient, 0, 1.
But I could write anything,
17 and 34, whatever.
I can make it using u and v,
which means no matter what third
vector I write in R2, the
collection is going to be
linearly dependent.
Yeah,
good.
Now if this were instead a
question in R3,
like if I start with 1 0 0 and 0
1 0, again starting with these
just because the numbers are
convenient,
the third vector I write could
make the set linearly,
it could keep it linearly
independent or
it may be linearly dependent.
So can you tell me a third
vector I could write that makes
this set linearly independent?
Yeah?
0, 0, 1.
That's the convenient answer I
was going for.
But just to make it clear that
it doesn't need to be 0, 0, 1,
let's just write something else,
1, 2, negative 15.
OK?
Also linearly independent,
because you can't get a negative
15 in the third component using
just the first two vectors.
So I have three linearly
independent vectors in R3 here.
They span all of R3.
Because these first two span
just the xy plane.
This third thing is not on the
plane, so it allows me to
levitate off.
That's the way that you should
think about this
What if I started with 1 0 0
0 1 0 and my third vector was I
Don't know give me a third
vector that would make this set
linearly dependent
There's lots of answers you
could give yeah 1 1 0 1 1 0
again just to make it clear that
it doesn't have to just be there
some let's put something random
Okay, pick two random numbers
Pi e0.
Sure.
This is linearly dependent.
That's because the third vector
can be made with the first two.
What that means is you can make
the second vector with the first
and the third.
You can do the first vector
minus the first vector times 1
over e minus pi times the third
vector.
you can make any one of those
using the other two.
So that collection on the bottom
is linearly dependent.
The collection on the top is
linearly independent.
There's no way to make any one
of those using the other two.
So this is a good example that
crystallizes the key idea here.
And everything we just discussed
about linear combinations being
unique is inherited by these two
sets of vectors,
meaning any linear combination
of these three can only be made
in one way.
There's only one recipe that
will get you any particular
output.
On the bottom here, because
these vectors are linearly
dependent,
if there's a vector you can make
with them,
you can make that vector
infinitely many ways.
Okay.
Paul.
Do vectors have to be in the
same dimension to say whether
they're independent?
Yes.
Or the same,
they need to have the same
number of components.
Yes.
Is dimension the wrong word?
Dimension means something very
specific, which I was going to
define today.
We'll define it on Thursday.
But dimension is a property of a
subspace,
not of a vector individually is
the way I want you to think of
that.
OK.
The final thing I wanted to say
is
that, OK,
let's consider this plane.
This will be a nice segue to
what I wanted to get to.
This plane contains the vectors
v1, v2, and v3.
But what we've learned is that
you only need two vectors in R3
to span a plane.
Why? Because a plane is a
two-dimensional thing.
There's only two directions on
which you can think of it like a
sheet of paper.
It only has like two independent
directions.
So once you have those two
independent vectors, you have
the plane, you don't need the
third one.
Okay,
so a question one might ask is
Find the like minimum
number of building blocks you
need to make this plane
Okay
So here's a question that may
look something like this.
Here are five vectors in R3
We know that since we have five
vectors, but they live in R3.
This collection can't be
linearly independent because R3
See,
the max dimension that these
vectors could span is three,
which means you only need three
of them to span whatever these
all span,
okay?
They could all live on the same
line.
Looking at the numbers, you know
that they don't, because they're
not all scalar multiples of each
other.
They could all live on the same
plane, or they may not.
They may just be vectors in R3,
but we know you only need three
linearly independent vectors in
R3 to span all of R3.
So in any case,
we know that these five vectors
are not linearly independent.
Are we clear on that?
OK.
Now the question is,
can I extract a subset of these
vectors that are linearly
independent
and have the same span?
The answer is yes.
And what the notes in chapter
4.2
at the bottom walk you through
is how you might do that.
And essentially,
the technique is just this.
The order in which the vectors
were written doesn't matter, but
here's just one way you could
find a linearly independent
subset.
Paste this here
with
the same span.
Actually, I want to hear that
from you.
I have these five vectors.
They span something.
It might be a line, might be a
plane, might be all of our
three.
How can I pull out a linearly
independent subset of them that
has the same span?
How can I find a subset of these
five vectors this,
where that subset has the same
span as all five of them.
Any ideas?
Yeah?
So the main idea here is trying
to see,
sort of as you alluded to,
if you can make some of these
vectors with the others.
OK? Now there's not just one
answer to this question Like it
could be that these three span
the same thing as all five and
so do these three and so do
these three Those all may span
the same thing as all five of
them But one way you could find
one subset with the same span is
to just read the vectors from
left to right and What you do
each time you arrive at a new
vector is say hey Can I make
this with the building blocks of
already collected if I can
ignore it if I can't let's
collect it So reading from left
to right if my the first vector
I see is three four zero.
Well, I haven't collected
anything So I'm gonna add it to
my set of building blocks.
Okay,
what's my next vector?
0 1 1 can I make that with
anything I've seen so far?
No, you can't make that with
three four zero.
So let's include it.
What's the next vector?
V 3 negative 3 negative 2 2 can
I make that with the first two
building blocks? I collected
maybe I don't know you could
maybe you can okay And that's
where you'd have to solve to see
if you can make it.
If you can make it, you ignore
it, because it's redundant.
If bringing it along would make
the collection linearly
dependent.
But if you can't make it, well
then you put it into your bag,
and then you stop, because you
have three linearly independent
vectors in R3.
So that process you'll get
practice with in tomorrow's lab
and in this week's homework.
Yeah, Thiago? If you could make
it, you dropped them? If you
could make it you would not
include it in your subset
Exactly you keep all the new
vectors that you can't make with
the things you've already
collected
It's like, it's like so,
I need to start a fire.
More legible,
or less legible.
Wait, I literally walked in
here,
like you started talking about
this thing,
and you're like,
wait,
no, I don't have time for this.
five years total, so is that?
Yeah.
It's kind of hard to understand,
but I feel that.
Wait, which vector do you have
to say?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like what?
Literally the only thing I've
done that's like the same.
Yeah.
From?
The summer.
We don't see vectors that are
hidden.
We say this is the span of these
vectors, and this one other
vector may or may not
for example
one zero and zero
one span the same thing like one
one
and one They both,
like, this is all of R2, this is
also all of R2.
No,
there is.
The connection,
well,
the definition of span does not
require you to know anything
about linearity, which is why I
talked about span last week.
The span is just the set of all
linear combinations.
What we're seeing is that, and
like the idea we were getting at
with this thing that I just
wrote on the board,
is that when you have a
collection of vectors that are
not linearly independent,
you can remove some of them
while keeping the span the same
which is what we did here,
right? Like these vectors,
their span is all of R2.
But you only need two vectors to
span all of R2 so I can delete
this and the span doesn't
change.
That's the main idea.
Also the last thing, when you're
seeing if vectors are
independent, is there like a
shortcut you're doing in your
head or are you basically doing
like system equations?
Mostly systems, I mean like, I'm
not gonna have you do that a
ton.
There are some you got like
really quickly.
Well, if these two,
the first vector I saw,
there's nothing else, so I'm
going to include it.
And the second one, I don't need
to set up a system.
If this were in the span of the
first one, it would just be
something times 340,
but it's not because I have a
non-zero number there.
And this third one, I don't
know.
I would have to set up this
system.
Okay.
Thank you.
Good one.
And congrats again.
Thank you.
So it's not about the question,
so I'll save it for the exam,
but I don't think I'll be able
to make it because I have the...
What class is that?
Oh,
that's 388.